Before I got baptized,

I had a meeting with the priest.

These meetings are not typically held,

but seeing as I was a unique circumstance,

the meeting was arranged.

I went with my mom.

We drove to St. Stephen’s Episcopalian church on St. Stephen’s Drive.

We attended this church,

not because we were especially Episcopalian,

but because it was the closest to our house.

I could walk home from Sunday school,

my big sister with me,

traipsing down narrow potholed roads in our church clothes and church shoes,

costumes now,

unzipped from their religious context.

On the way to the meeting,

from the backseat, I asked my mom, “Where are we going?”

“To the Priest’s house,” she told me,

but we were driving the exact same way we took to go to church.

In the car:

I trade off looking out the window and the ghostly

reflection of my face

floating in the glass

mostly eyes and eyebrows.

I roll the window down and the ghost goes away.

“It’s not even cold,” I say.

It turned out that the priest’s house is right next to the church,

just back behind the parking lot,

behind the playground that burned down.

No one knew how the playground caught fire,

but later when I was in high school my friend told me that she knew how,

because it was her brother who burned it down,

which made sense because they lived right across the street at 65 St. Stephen’s Drive

and her brother was a bit of a pyromaniac.

Antes de que me bautizaron,

tuve una junta con el sacerdote.

Era una junta especial,

pero viendo que mi caso también era especial,

convocaran a la junta.

Mi mamá me llevó.

Manejamos hacia La Iglesia Episcopal de Santo Stefano

por la Calle Santo Stefano.

Íbamos allí a esa iglesia no por que era una iglesia episcopal,

si no porque quedaba cerca de casa.

Podríamos volver caminando,

mi hermana y yo,

caminando por las calles angostas y bacheadas, l

as ropas de iglesia ahora un disfraz,

ya sacado de su contexto de religión.

En el camino hacia la iglesia, pregunté a mi mamá,

¿“A dónde vamos?”

Me dijo, a la casa del sacerdote,

pero era igual al camino que tomábamos a irnos à la iglesia.

En el carro:

Miro por la ventana y luego por mi cara

flotando como fantasma en el vidrio.

Bajo la ventana y la fantasma se va

“No hace ni frio” digo yo.

Se resulta que la casa del sacerdote es el vecino de la iglesia,

detrás del parqueadero

y atrás del parque infantil que se quemó.

Nadie sabía como se hubiera incendiado,

pero luego, luego, cuando estaba en el colegio,

me dijo mi amiga que ella si sabía como, por que era su hermano que lo hizo.

Lo creí por que vivían en frente de la iglesia y también su hermano era medio pirómano.

The priest’s front room looked normal, nothing religious, and the priest did too.

There was a couch facing 2 chairs and in between them a lamp,

whose cord tunneled in a lump under the rug

on its way to the plug in the wall.

The only special thing about the priest’s front room

was the stained-glass window,

casting streaks of pink and blue onto

a little cluttered desk

off to the left.

I sat in the gap

where the couch cushions met

but didn’t fully come together.

If the spot is available,

I always take it,

and that’s because the gap between couch cushions

is the most comfortable spot.

On the couch:

I look at the stained-glass window and close my eyes

I see rows and rows of windmills.

I am still looking at the stained-glass, even though my eyes are closed.

It’s supposed to be black when you hide your eyes, but the light can still peep through the crack

like breath between closed lips

and it makes colors appear in the darkness.

The windmills are bright and flickery like flame.

I opened my eyes and the windmills disappear.

In their place was the priest’s round and folded face

He’d been saying something

to my mom.

On the couch still:

I close my eyes tighter and the rows of

windmills back up and get smaller

All perfectly straight and as many as can fit on the black screen of my

eyelids.

When the screen fills,

the windmills shrink again, allowing

space for more rows of more

windmills.

And on it goes, the rows filling the darkness

between my open eyes and closed eyelids.

The space endless and ever accommodating

the unrelenting accumulation of forever.

La sala del sacerdote se veía muy normal, nada religioso, y el sacerdote también.

Había un sofá en frente y

entre de dos sillones, una lámpara

su cable parecía topo pasando por abajo el alfombre hacia el enchufe en el muro.

La única cosa especial de la sala era el vitral

pintando rayos rosados y azulados sobre una mesita desordenada

a la izquierda.

Me sentí en el hueco del sofá

Siempre, si podía, me sentaba allí,

donde los dos cojines se juntan

porque así es lo más cómodo.

Sentado en el sofa:

Miro al vitral

Cierro mis ojos, pero sigo mirándolo.

Veo hilera tras hilera de alas de molino.

Dicen que solo ves negro cuando los ojos se cierran,

pero la luz puede entrar a través de la rajadura del

párpado como aire entre labios cerrados

y hace aparecer los colores en medio de la oscuridad.

Las alas brillan

bastante y como llama

parpadean.

Abrí mis ojos y se desaparecieron las alas.

En su lugar estaba el cara redondo y plisado

del sacerdote.

Había estado diciendo algo

a mi mama.

Todavía en el sofa:

Cierro mis ojos con más fuerza y las alas del molino

se retiran y se encogieren.

Todas derechitas y tantas como pudieran caber

en la pantalla negra que formaban mis párpados.

Cuando se llenó la pantalla,

se encogieren otra vez las alas para que cupieran

aun más.

Así se fue, hileras llenando la oscuridad

entre los ojos y párpados.

El espacio sin parar, las alas

volviendo, siguiendo hasta

siempre.

My mom sat in a big arm chair next to the priest.

I think his name was Father Tom, but I couldn’t be sure

because there was also Father Paul who looked a lot like

Father Tom.

That morning:

I lean in close to the mirror

and look at my hairs right down to their

follicles, where they sprout out

of the hole in

my scalp. For every

hair, a hole, a head

full of holes.

I had never seen the priest this close up before.

My view of him had always been from afar,

in the pews, and often partially blocked by a head

so that I would watch him and see

a priest with no chin.

Or, a priest with only half a face, reciting the Lord’s prayer.

I had a chance to see him up close on the way out,

when he stood there shaking hands

at the doors that let forth

the tide of Episcopalians,

picking wedgies and squinting into the late Sunday morning light, and I within it, catching only a

blurred glimpse of him.

My friend with the pyromaniac brother,

she told me not to tell anyone that it was her brother

who burned down the playground.

I didn’t,

not that it mattered anyway.

It had been so long ago by then.

They’d used the parish dollars to reconstruct it.

I always brought a dollar with me to church.

A single crisp extraction

from my weekly allowance

that I put in an otherwise empty purse that I carried

as a means of carrying my dollar.

Mi mama se sentó en un sillón al lado del sacerdote.

Creo que se llamó Padre Tom, pero no podría estar segura

porque también era un Padre Paul

quien parecía mucho a Padre Tom.

Aquella manana:

Me acerco al espejo y miro a mis pelos hasta

sus fondos, donde brota desde el hoyito

de la cabellera.

Un hoyito por cada pelo,

una cabeza

llena de hoyos.

Nunca había mirado el sacerdote de cerca así.

Siempre lo había mirado de lejos en el banco

donde solía que una cabeza de adelante bloqueaba mi vista resultando que pasara todo el sermón mirando un sacerdote

sin mentón,

o un sacerdote recitando el padrenuestro de un solo lado de su cara.

Tenía oportunidad a verlo a la salida,

cuando se estacionaba en la puerta para dejar correr

el rio de creyentes acomodándose sus medias, sus calzones después del rato sentados,

encandilándose con la luz de la mañana,

el río que me llevaba tal que lo que alcanzara a ver del sacerdote era un

vistazo movido.

Mi amiga, la que tiene el hermano medio pirómano,

ella me pidió a que no le dijera a nadie.

A no decir que fue su hermano el que quemó el parque infantil.

No dije nada, aunque no importaba mucho.

Ya estaba años atrás.

Habían pagado por uno nuevo con el dinero de la parroquia.

Yo siempre traía un dólar conmigo a la iglesia.

Una única y crujiente extracción de mi domingo que era la única cosa

que tenía en la cartera que llevé,

y la única razón para que la llevara.

I took out my dollar when the time came.

The time came when the two men,

on a cue beknown only to them,

stood

up from their deliberate seats at the end of the pews,

disappeared discretely through a doorway

to the left of the crucifix, and returned again,

on cue,

bearing gold platters with curled over rims and black velvet lined interiors.

During collection:

I ready my dollar as the dish approaches,

handed over, hand to hand, skip a hand, to hand,

gliding down the pews as if levitating on the notes of

the organ and not by the hands that reach and pass

this thing impossible to drop.

The dish bearers flank each side of the pews,

One down the center aisle, one down the outer aisle,

trading their dishes back and

forth, back and forth,

as soon as he passes, he is walking forward a row to

receive the other, the same dish he sent down to his

partner,

two rows ago, it’s hard to know,

now it’s coming back to him, fuller now, my dollar in there,

the organist playing, his back to us,

our backs to him.

“Now, why do you want to be baptized?” the priest asked me.

I thought about this,

which I had not done before.

I had never considered a baptism as something I wanted;

it was just something that my mom informed me was happening.

I looked to my mom a beat,

for both assistance and permission

to stretch the truth.

“Well,” I began while attempting to level myself on the couch but finding myself

already too deeply absorbed

into the gap.

“All my relatives are baptized and I don’t want to be left out.”

My mom nodded in a way that granted me

further permission to elaborate on the truth so I added,

“Besides, I’ve always really wanted a godmother and godfather.”

Mientras la colecta:

Sacaba mi dolar cuando era el momento.

El momento llegó cuando los dos señores,

siguiendo el ritmo que solo ellos sabían,

se levantaran a pies de sus asientos elegidos á propósito a la orilla de los bancos,

se desaparecieran discretamente a través del portal

a la izquierda del crucifico,

y volvieran de nuevo, listos, llevando canastos doradas con sus bordes doblados

y línea de terciopelo negro adentro.

Tengo mi dolaré listo mientras el canasto anda

acercando, entregada, deslizando de un lado al

otro de los bancos como si fuera levitado del

ritmo de las notas del órgano y no de las manos

que la alcanzaran y la pasaran,

este objeto, imposible a dejar caer.

Los señores de los canastos se pusieran a los dos lados de

los bancos, uno por el surco adentro, el otro por afuera.

Así andaban, pasando sus canastos.

Entregando una, un banco adelante, recibiendo la otra.

Ida y vuelta, como aguja en tejido, siempre un plato en las manos, siempre una fuente

flotando en el banco. Nunca vacía,

el órgano soñando, los canastos llenando.

“Por que quieres ser bautizada?” me preguntó el sacerdote.

Pensé en eso por primera vez.

Nunca lo había considerado como algo que quería

si non un evento que iba a ocurrir según mi mama.

Le eché un vistazo en lo que pedí

ayuda y permiso

a exagerar.

Dije “Bueno,” mientras que intentaba a salirme del hueco

donde ya profundamente había hundido.

“Todos mis parientes lo tuvieran, y yo también quiero uno.”

Mi mama parpadeó para decir que estuvo bien y para darme

mas permiso a seguir elaborando la verdad.

“Y siempre he querido tener un padrino y madrina,” dije.

This seemed to do it for the priest because

he nodded and told me about the history of baptisms,

how traditionally they are performed in a river,

but now they just use a little bowl of holy water.

“Do they get the water from a river?” I asked.

He paused, looked to my mom, and said, “Yes.”

And then more to himself he said,

“All water comes from the river.”

I wondered which river he was referring to exactly but I let it slide

in exchange for his unblinking acceptance of my own white lie.

He explained how baptisms play an important role

in welcoming new members to the faith

and perpetuating life after death.

“You see, the religion you are is the religion you are baptized into,” the priest said.

“Only once you have been baptized Episcopalian, are you truly an Episcopalian. ”

He paused and his leather shoe toed the lump in the rug where it arched for the cable.

“And when you go to heaven, your spirit will live on through your faith.”

He nodded his own head in agreement,

so that I would see that what he said made sense.

He stood up and mom and I, we did the same,

just as in church after a prayer, except that

I had to hoist myself up with my arms, and pump my legs,

on account of my being so deeply seated within the couch.

Esta calificó como respuesta válida por el sacerdote

porque prosiguióa explicarme la historia de los bautismos,

y como antes lo hicieron en el rio,

pero hace algunos años remplazaron el rio con fuentes

de agua sagrada.

“Pero el agua viene del rio?” le pregunté.

Se paró para mirar a mi mama, y dijo, “Si, el agua viene del rio.”

Y luego más a su mismo comentó,

“Bueno, toda el agua viene del rio.”

Le iba a preguntar, cual río pues,

pero lo dejé pasar.

Se me explicó que los bautismos

desempeñan un papel importante por los creyentes

de bienvenida y despedida.

“Mira, de que religión eres depende en la religión que tiene tu bautismo,” dijo el sacerdote.

“No eres episcopal hasta que estés bautizado episcopal.”

Hacía una pausa mientras su zapato de cuero tocaron el topo del alfombre.

“Y cuando vayas con dios, tu espíritu sigue por siempre a través de tu fe.”

Se asintió con su propia cabeza para que viera que lo que dijo tenía sentido.

Se puso a pies y lo seguimos, igual que en la iglesia

cuando nos levantamos después de una oración

a parte de aquí tenía que luchar un poquito a salirme

por culpa de mi asiento profundo en el sofá.

At night:

I am scared to die.

I think about it before falling asleep.

It is not so much the act of dying that I am scared of or

think about, It is the fact that once you die you are

gone

Forever and ever and ever and

ever and I keep repeating the ever’s

filling the time, filling my mind, my head heavy on

my pillow, eyelashes fluttering against its case,

with the repetition of ever

But no matter how many times I repeat, it will never amount to the

forever of time That will go on

without me

once I’m dead.

Eye blinks, even when closed.

It was time for the tour.

We went out the front door and crossed the empty parking lot

and entered the church through a side door I’d never noticed before.

The door opened up into an unceremonious carpeted room

with a vase of plastic flowers on a folding table.

I watched my mom’s hand

as it took a papery pink petal between its fingers,

palpating to confirm that the flowers were

in fact, fake.

Then we went into a little hallway where there was a sliding closet door.

“This is where we get ready for the sermon,” the Priest explained.

He slid open the door and all his costumes were hanging up in there

—the purple one for lent, the white one for regular Sundays, a few of those;

the gold one for Christmas Eve and Easter,

and a red one for an occasion I had never attended church to see.

The other costumes I had seen from the audience,

from a distance long enough to soften

the stiffness of the fabric, its coarseness,

the wide stitch dragging its off-white trail of thread through

the bulky hem of the white sleeve.

The gold platters were stacked on a wide ledge carved out of the wall and below,

the candle snuffers that the acolytes carry

were propped up in an umbrella stand.

En la noche:

Me asusto de morirme.

Pienso en lo antes de dormir.

No es el acto de morirme que me asuste

sino la idea de siempre.

Que una vez que te mueras,

te vas por siempre y siempre

y siempre y sigo repitiendo los siempres llenando el tiempo,

llenando mi cabeza pesada sobre

cabecera pestañas palpitando

con la repetición de la palabra

pero no importa cuantas veces lo digo nunca alcanzará

al tiempo de siempre que va a seguir

sin mi

una vez que me muera.

Las pestañas palpitan aun con ojos cerrados.

Empezamos el tour. Salimos de la puerta principal

y cruzamos el parqueadero vacío de carros

y entramos la iglesia por una puerta que nunca había notado.

La puerta se abría en un cuarto brusco

y alfombrado con un vaso de flores de plástico encima

de una mesa plegable. Miré como la mano de mi mama tomó el

tallo de alambre entre sus dedos

a sentir su verdadera falsedad.

Seguíamos por el corredor donde había una puerta corredera de ropera.

“Aquí es donde nos preparamos por el sermón,” el sacerdote explicó.

Recorrió la puerta y se veía sus disfraces colgando—

el morado por la Cuaresma, el blanco de siempre, varios así;

el dorado por la navidad y la Pasque y un rojo por una ocasión que nunca había visto.

Los demás los había visto del público,

desde una distancia que borra la rigidez de la tela, su aspereza;

el punto ancho arrastrando

su hilo color crema haciendo la gruesa dobladilla de la manga color blanca.

Los platos dorados estaban amontonados encima

un estante y abajo,

los apagavelas que llevaron los acólitos estaban sostenidos en un paragüero.

The communion wafers were on the ledge too.

I hardly recognized them at first.

They were in large plastic tub with a screw top cap,

same as the tubs peanut-butter stuffed pretzels come in.

“My daughter likes these in her lunch,” the Priest said while unscrewing the lid.

He took out a few discs, fine as paper

and popped two into his mouth.

“Here, have a few,” he said and I held out my hands,

palms up, pinky sides pressed together,

just as I’d learned to do for communion.

It felt strange to have more in my hand at one time

than I’d accumulate in an entire month of steady church attendance,

so I ate them slowly which wasn’t hard to do

on account of their tasting very

stale and dy.

On the way home, I asked my mom,

“How many days a week is church?”

“One day a week, 2 sermons on Sunday.”

“What does the priest do on the other days?” I asked.

“Preparing his sermon,” my mom said. “Practicing and preparing.”

At the pool:

I go under water.

A clear blue I can’t hear or breath.

I look to the surface

Slick lid of ice

I wait in the slow quiet and then it

breaks into

turbulence like a million marbles bursting free

close, but sounds far

away I come up for

air.

I wore a white dress to my baptism.

My mom had bought two matching ones

from a consignment store that my sister and I wore

for our Christmas card photo one year.

Only difference was that I didn’t have to wear it with tights,

since the baptism was in spring.

Allá por el mismo estante, estaban las hostias.

Casi no las reconocí.

Estaban en un grande jarro de plástico, con tapón de rosca

como si fueran una botana de la tienda.

“Mi hija se les gustan en su lonche,” el sacerdote dijo mientras desenroscando el tapón.

Tomó algunos de los discos delgaditos como una hoja,

y de un solo golpe los pegó dos por su lengua.

“Toma,” me dijo. “Ten.”

Extendí mis manos, palmas arriba, lados de meniques juntados,

igual como había aprendido hacer por la comunión.

Se sentía raro a tener en mis manos mas hostias que acumulara

aún después un mes de ir a la iglesia,

y por eso los comí despacio,

lo que por su sabor sin sabor

no era muy difícil.

A la vuelta a casa, pregunté a mi mama,

“Cuantos días la semana hacen iglesia ¿”

“Uno nomas,” me contestó. “Dos sermones el domingo.”

“Y que hace el sacerdote los otros días?” pregunté.

“Preparándose,” dijo mi mama. “Preparando su sermón.”

A la alberca:

Me hundo en el agua azul claro

donde no respiro ni escucho.

Miro hacia la superficie

un cielo como techo de hielo fino.

Espero en el silencio lento y de repente

quiebra.

Agua revuelto, burbujas,

tiradas como canicas,

ruido cercas, pero se escucha

lejos, subo por

aire.

Me vestía en vestido blanco a mi bautismo.

Mi mamá había comprado dos igualitos para que

mi hermana y yo pudiera estar correspondiente

por la foto de la tarjeta de Navidad.

La única diferencia era que no tenía que ponerme en medias,

dado que estábamos en primavera.

The baptism was held after normal church service,

after everyone had left. Only the families with infants and my family remained.

We scooted into the front pews and it all felt so unprofessional I thought,

like a dress rehearsal instead of the real thing.

Except the priest.

He didn’t look at me as someone who knew the color of his sofa,

who had seen the closet from where he’d picked out today’s robe,

the usual white.

He looked at me the same as he looked at the babies,

who had no idea what holy water was, or where it came from.

The mothers and fathers held their infants and we gathered

around a little basin of water suspended in a mini altar.

The babies were dressed in soft white cotton

with bunchy little socks on their feet

that could have made some nice finger puppets for me.

I rolled out onto the sides of my feet and balanced like this, on the outer edges of the soles

of my kitty-heeled shoes. I felt very big and embarrassing.

I wanted to be a baby in soft cotton

held in my mother’s arms.

The priest peeled the first baby out of the crook of its father’s elbow.

He hovered the baby right over the basin of holy water,

but instead of dunking its head in,

he just scooped up some holy water and splashed it

onto the baby’s matted little head.

The baby squirmed and kicked but did not cry out

so I figured that holy water must not to be too cold.

The priest went to hand the brand, new Episcopalian baby

back to the father but the mother instinctively reached out her arms,

catching the priest

in a moment of vacillation not knowing

whose arms to put the baby in.

Now the baby did start to cry, and the mother armed with responsibility

took the small thing off the priest’s hands.

El bautismo tomó lugar después de la mesa normal,

después que todos había partidos.

La congregación se filtraba hasta que las únicas familias

que quedaron eran las familias con bebés

y yo con mi familia.

Nos fuimos hasta los primeros bancos,

todo muy burdo pensé yo,

como si fuera banco a un partido de futbol en vez de un bautismo.

No sentía nada de obra final.

Aparte del sacerdote.

No me miraba como alguien que sabía el color de su sofá,

que había visto de donde sacó la mera sotana que ahora llevó,

el blanco de siempre.

Me miraba igual que miraba a los bebés,

a quien ni tenían idea de lo que es agua sagrada, ni de donde viene.

Las mamás y los papás abrazaron sus bebés y acercamos alrededor

un pequeño fuente del agua suspendido en un altarcito.

Los bebés se vestirían en algodón blanco y suave,

con pliegues de encaje y calcetines arrugados por sus pies de hada.

Me equilibraba sobre los lados de mis tacos bajos. Sentía mi tamaño como una bochorno.

Quisiera estar un bebe vestido en algodón,

abrazado en los brazos de mi mama.

El sacerdote peleó el primero bebe del recodo del brazo de su papa.

Lo sobrevoló el bebe sobre el cuenco de agua sagrada,

pero en vez de empapando su cabeza,

lo mojó el frente con algunas salpicaduritas y ya.

Bautizado.

El bebe se retorció y pegó sus pies de hada al aire, pero no lloró,

lo que me significó que el agua sagrada no era tan fría.

El sacerdote pasó el nuevo Episcopal a su papa,

pero se extendió a la misma vez las manos de la mama lo que agarró

el sacerdote en un momento de incertidumbre y ahora si,

el bebe empezó a llorar,

lo que dio a la mama su oportunidad claro

a arrancar su responsabilidad de los brazos vestidos del sacerdote.

I felt nervous as my turn approached. I was the elephant in the room,

this enormous overgrown baby.

If only someone had just asked why, if someone could have just said

‘Well you sure are a big one, aren’t you?”,

I could’ve explained that actually I was born a long time ago, and it’s only now

7 and a half years later, that my parents,

mostly my mom, got around to getting me baptized.

But nobody asked.

My appointed godparents rose up from the pew

when the priest announced me. They came to stand by my side.

My godmother is my paternal aunt, whose birthday is a day before mine

and my godfather is my uncle, no blood relation of mine, but from my mom’s side.

It was strange to see the two sides side by side like that.

Like two days in a row and no night in between, it didn’t make sense.

At this age:

I believe in Heaven not because it’s what the Bible says

But because I am too small to fathom

how people could write stories and sing songs and build

buildings and pray prayers

for something that could

might possibly

did

not

exist.

The priest dipped his finger in the holy water

and fingerpainted a cross on my forehead.

The water felt cool and dewy for a moment,

and then dripped down the bridge of my nose

and slipped onto my eyelid, where it balanced until

I blinked

and it slid down my cheek like a tear.

I had to resist the urge to wipe if off, because, what a waste.

I don’t think smeared off holy water does any good.

After the ceremony everyone relaxed and cooed at the adorable baptized babies.

My uncle, now godfather, picked me up

and pretended to dunk me head first into the holy water

which made me feel better,

like finally someone had acknowledged my tremendous size.

Me sentía nerviosa mientras que mi turno se acercaba.

Era el elefante en la sala, esta bebe grandulona.

Si alguien me hubiera preguntado dicho algo,

si alguien me hubiera preguntado: ‘como creciste tanto ¿’

pudiera explicar que de hecho nací hace algunos años,

y apenas ahora, siete años y media después,

mis papas—mayormente mi mama,

se organizaron a bautizarme,

pero nadie me preguntó.

Mi padrino y madrina designado se pararon del banco

y acercaron al altarcito cuando el sacerdote me presentó.

Mi madrina es mi tía paternal, la que tiene su cumpleaños un día antes del mío,

y mi padrino es mi tío, no es un consanguíneo mío, pero viene del lado de mi mama.

Era raro a ver los dos lados de la familia así hombro à hombro,

como dos días seguidos sin una noche a separarlos.

A esta edad:

Creo en el cielo no porque es lo que dice la Biblia,

sino porque estoy demasiado pequeña para entender

como la gente pudiera escribir historias y cantar canciones y construir

edificios y orar oraciones

por algo que posiblemente

no

exista.

El sacerdote mojó su dedo en el agua sagrada

y pintó el cruce en mi frente.

El agua sentía fresca como rocío hasta que

se goteó en mi parpado, donde se equilibró hasta que

parpadeé

y se deslizó por mi cachete como lagrima lenta.

Después la ceremonia todo se relajaron

y arrullaban a los bebes bautizados.

Mi tío ahora padrino me agarró en sus brazos

y fingió a hundirme de cabeza en el agua sagrada.

Eso me hizo sentir mejor.

Que por fin alguien se daba cuenta de mi

tamaño tremendo.

At a stop sign:

We drive home from the baptism.

Mom said not to walk.

We pull up behind a truck who stops

long enough to open his door just enough to slam it back shut.

The air was getting in.

We had a party in our back patio with my new godparents

and our other relatives. It felt like a mix between my birthday party and Easter.

My grandma gave me a little pink bible that has ‘My Old Testament’

embossed on the cover in gold print.

You open it up and the whole bible is right there,

typed out in miniature letters on to crinkly pages thin as crepe paper.

“It can fit in your pocket, but the magnifying glass you’ll need to read it won’t,” my dad said.

He is not a religious man, I later realized, though he has deep beliefs.

He always stayed seated in the pews during communion.

My uncle turned godfather,

I later discovered once he wasn’t anymore,

had been an alcoholic. He gave up drinking

and found God through a Bible study and

joined a mega church that has Christian rock concerts

built into the Sunday service.

At the library:

I sit next to a man surrounded by books scribbling away like a college student.

The books I realize are all the same, are all different versions of the same.

Bibles. He has one open to a page and off the page I read—

It is sown a natural body, it is raised a spiritual body. If there is a natural body—

but then his hand

covers the rest.

My aunt turned godmother got in a disagreement with my Dad

over the circumstances of my grandmother’s will.

She thought it meant one thing, and my dad thought it said

quite clearly something else.

A una señal de alto:

Manejamos a casa después del bautizo.

Mama no nos dejo caminar.

Llegamos detrás una camioneta que para lo suficiente

para abrir su puerta lo suficiente para cerrarla de nuevo.

Estaba dejando entrar el aire.

Tuvimos una fiesta en el patio con mis nuevos padrinos y mis parientes.

Se sentía como mezcla de mi cumpleaños y la Pasque.

Mi abuela me regaló una rosada biblia pequeñita que dijo

‘Mi Antiguo Testamento’ grabado en el forro en letras doradas.

La abres y allí esta la biblia entera,

escrito en letras chiquititas en hojas mas finas que pétalo de flor.

“Se cabe en tu bolsita, pero la lupa que vas a ocupar a leerle, no,” dijo mi papa.

El no es un hombre religioso, me daba cuenta luego, aunque tenga sus creencias profundas.

Siempre se quedaba sentado mientras la comunión.

Mi tío, ahora padrino era un alcohólico.

Pero luego dejó de tomar y encontró dios a través

un estudio de la Biblia.

Ahora toma pura agua con gas.

En la biblioteca:

Me siento a una mesa, a lado de un señor

trabajando, pero como burro, rodeado de libros.

Veo que los libros son versiones de la misma cosa,

la Biblia.

Tiene una abierta a una pagina y esta escribiendo. Alcanzo leer—

Se siembre un cuerpo natural,

se resucita un cuerpo espiritual. Si hay cuerpo—

pero luego su mano tapa

lo demás.

Mi tía, ahora madrina discutió con mi papa

sobre los detalles del testamento de mi abuela.

Ella pensó que dijo una cosa, y mi papa pensó

que claramente dijo otra cosa.

I didn’t see my godmother aunt for several years and didn’t respond to her messages either.

Then my dad forgave her

and she came back to Christmas dinner as if nothing had ever happened.

No miraba a mi tía mientras algunos años

hasta que mi papa la perdonó

y regresó a la cena navideña como nunca nada había pasado.